YWCA of the U.S.A. Records. Record Group 6. Program: Series IV. Constituent Groups
Sophia Smith Collection
See also the personal papers of Dorothy Spellman, R. Elizabeth Johns, Norma Stauffer, and Dorothy Height; and the Southern Women, the Student YWCA, and Race (1920-1944) Collection.
SUBSERIES D. TEEN-AGE AND YOUNGER GIRLS Historical Note
YWCA work with young girls began in the U.S. as early as 1881 with the founding of the Little Girls' Christian Association of Oakland, California. Girls' YWCA Clubs were formed in City Associations, in private high schools under the auspices of the Student Department (which had responsibility for the "older younger girl"), in churches, and, in parts of the country where there was no nearby YWCA, they were sometimes established in public high schools.
At the time of the founding of the National Association in 1906-07 there were so many younger girls taking part in the movement that the first national conference of YWCA employed officers in 1909 took as its general topic "The Young Girl." Across the country and without much supervision, the girls had proved themselves "on hand and not under foot" (Elizabeth Wilson Fifty Years of Association Work Among Young Women) to such a degree that the National Association took note and began to coordinate the work.
The National Association added a Special Worker for Junior Work to the City Department in the Department of Method in 1911. After studying the situation, she concluded that the Association would only "obtain satisfactory results" by placing the junior work "on a par with all other departmental work being done in local Associations," noting that this would never be accomplished "so long as the junior work is regarded as an appendage to be tolerated, rather than as a legitimate piece of Association work."
Many Community Associations proceeded to establish a "Junior Department" to oversee Clubs and activities for members between the ages of ten and sixteen. They were encouraged to hire trained Secretaries dedicated to the work. "It began to be recognized by all that, if the Association movement was really to help girls to help themselves to become women citizens of intelligence and power, there must be secretaries in the movement who understood educational methods of work with girls of this age." ("History of the Growth of Work with Younger Girls in the YWCA," by Gertrude Gogin, The Workshop Series no. 1, circa 1927)
The new Girls Work Secretaries, began experimenting with the "fundamentals of character-building work with girls." A plethora of names and schemes emerged for these groups, among them "Rainbow Clubs" for very young girls, "Be Square Clubs" for young working girls, and for the rest, "Girl Aides," "Silver Link Girls," "Four Square Girls," and "Triangle Girls." Concurrently, the National Association encouraged a new approach to Association work in general, seeking to adapt the organization to the girl rather than adapting the girl to the organization. The "most important principle beginning persistently to emerge was that a girl's real growth is dependent upon her learning for herself through experience." ("History of the Growth of Work with Younger Girls in the YWCA," by Gertrude Gogin, The Workshop Series no. 1, circa 1927) In order to be effective it could not be work "for" girls, but work "with" girls.
At Convention in 1913, the membership voted, at the request of the girls, to abandon the term "Junior Department" in favor of their preferred "Girls' Department" and in 1915 the age range for membership in Girls' programs was changed to twelve to eighteen years. The Eight Week Club scheme, inaugurated in the summer of 1913, paired college students home for the summer with younger girls to form clubs of "friendship and service" during the school vacation. The plan gave the college women a chance to practice their leadership skills and introduce a new generation to the work of the Association.
World War I brought about a desire in the general population to organize for community service. According to the new National Girls Work Secretary, Gertrude Gogin, this general desire came to include "the understanding that one of the most vital factors in community life was the girl in her teens." Gogin, began her work late in 1917 with six months' study of existing programs. She concluded that "the only way to have constructive work with younger girls was to have a national program which would bring about unity and standards to our work." "... [W]e have had any one of 57 varieties according to the taste and ability of our local Associations. This has meant no really constructive help from headquarters to fields nor from fields to locals. There was no means for transmitting ideas for everyone was doing something different." (Gertrude Gogin, Annual Report to the Department of Method, 1918)
To remedy this situation, the National Association established the Girl Reserve program, which was "born" in September of 1918. The National Association distributed written materials outlining "specific and different programs" for grade school girls, high school girls, and young employed girls (girls at work under age eighteen). At the same time Girls' Work Secretaries were added to nine of the Field staffs. Girl Reserve staff worked in close cooperation with the Student Department on the high school program and the Industrial Department on the program for young employed girls. Designed to give a sense of unity but not uniformity to the work, the program included special Girl Reserve songs, ceremonials, conferences, training programs, and a uniform.
In a statement written about 1923 at the request of the YMCA, Gertrude Gogin outlined the program and explained, "The name, 'Girl Reserve' is not a military term. A Girl Reserve is a girl who is constantly storing up, putting in reserve, more of those qualities which will help her to take her place as a Christian citizen in her home, her school, her church, and her community."
The earliest forms of organization for the youngest members were "Triangle Clubs," small groups of fifteen to twenty seventh and eighth graders. Senior high-school student clubs were self-governing with a slate of officers and standing committees. Young employed girls belonged to "YGBI" (Younger Girls in Business and Industry) Clubs, a program that placed a greater emphasis on recreation.
The rapidly increasing contingent of Girl Reserve Secretaries formed their own section of the National Association of Employed Officers at their 1922 meeting.
By 1927 Gogin described the work as "not a pattern program of work for girls, but... instead an evolving educational process of work with girls." It was a "movement" based on modern scientific educational methods, attempting "to help girls better to understand how to make right choices." ("History of the Growth of Work with Younger Girls in the YWCA," by Gertrude Gogin, The Workshop Series no. 1, circa 1927)
Publications were one of the primary contributions of the National Association to the movement. In addition to a lively and informative serial publication, known as The Bookshelf, the Womans Press cranked out a wide array of books, manuals, pamphlets, work tools, skits, etc., for the girls themselves, for their parents, and for their club leaders. Designed with the younger audience in mind, they deal with classic YWCA topics such as citizenship, religion, health, and interracial and international relations. The National Staff also made a sort of specialty of female adolescent development, writing books, articles, and pamphlets for use by the Association and the general public.
Many girls had their first YWCA exposure at summer camps run by Community Associations. By the late 1920s, the Girl Reserve Program included Regional Conferences for those who went on to deeper involvement with the Girl Reserve. GR Conferences, like those for other groups, combined recreational and educational activities. They offered experience in leadership, democracy in action, and community-building. All of the standard YWCA subjects were presented using techniques designed to be age-appropriate.
After World War II, the Association noted less interest among the girls in "long-continued club projects of a more serious nature," and increased desire for more informal recreational activities, particularly "good-times in the evening" in a co-educational (but chaperoned) setting. Ever younger members were requesting co-educational parties and the "help on boy-girl relationships." Program focused on "problems of social concern," career/work decisions, community service projects, the arts, and religion. ("New Times Bring New Ways of Work in the YWCA" by Elise Moller, Religious Education, March-April 1943)
As the program adjusted to the post-war world, it changed name to "Y-Teen" in 1946 "recognizing that youth is not merely in reserve to adulthood, but is a unique and important time of development." ("Youth Development in the YWCA: Goals and Issues," 1994) In 1947 the Y-Teens held their first joint high school conference with the YMCA. As with the college students, there was much interest among the girls in cooperative work with the YMCA in the 1940s and 1950s. In 1948, the National Association initiated "Teen Roll Call" (later known as "Y-Teen Week"), a campaign to build national and community support for the teen program. Y-Teens were invited to attend Convention as visiting delegates for the first time in 1949. The events included the first Teen Assembly.
It was not until 1956 that this younger constituency had its first National Conference. The emphasis for this and two later national conferences in 1959 and 1965 was youth's role in national and world affairs.
After World War II, the National Association eliminated or drastically cut back on Program for most constituent groups. By the 1960s, national programs were most likely to be short-term, funded through U.S. government or foundation grants, and run at a few Community Associations on a more-or-less "demonstration" basis as a means of devising program models that could be replicated by other organizations. They tended to be "problem-focused" and designed to serve youth in high risk environments. These programs included the Summer Youth Demonstration Project (1967), the National Youthworker Education Project (1970s), the Juvenile Justice Program (circa 1978-81); the Youth Employability Project (1980-83), the Teen Pregnancy Prevention Program (1980s), and Women as Preventors-An Adult-Teen Partnership dealing with issues related to alcohol abuse (1980s).
In response to student unrest and the youth movement of the late 1960s and early 1970s, a National Staff reorganization of the early 1970s briefly linked responsibility for teens, college students, and younger YWCA members in a Youth Constituencies Unit. In 1973 Convention voted to authorize a National Teen Organization to bring teens more directly into the National Association's decision-making process and the Convention voting age was lowered from seventeen to fifteen. It was an acknowledgment by the whole Association that its long term health depended on the involvement of its younger members.
One product of this era was the Teen Counseling Project of 1973-74. Though carried out in a different manner, the Project was essentially one more example of the traditional YWCA approach to its work, a study to determine the needs of the group. The National Teen Organization planned the project in cooperation with the YWCA Resource Center on Women and the Bank Street College of Education. Teens in four diverse communities (El Paso, Texas; Greenville, South Carolina; Philadelphia, Pennsylvania; and South Bend, Indiana) helped to design a questionnaire to collect information from teen women of widely diverse backgrounds. With the data collected, the Project gathered follow-up information by holding a workshop in each city for teens who had completed the questionnaires. Each workshop was planned and run by teens with help from two adult consultants.
Among the top priorities detailed in the Project's final report, "Attention is Needed Action is Called For: Teen Women Talk About Their Needs," were help in finding jobs and job training, sex education (particularly birth control information), more and better recreational opportunities, and drug information and rehabilitation programs.
In the late 1980s, the National Association obtained funding for production of three videos to present information about sexuality and pregnancy prevention to teens. "It's Okay to Say No Way!" (1986) is a music video "to convey a message in their medium, using their language." "Lovesick" and "Crush" (1989) were designed to encourage discussion and feature eleven to sixteen year olds talking about love, life, honesty, and friendship.
Another of the YWCA's periodic Studies to assess needs, the Youth Development Planning Project (1992-94), sought to change the emphasis of YWCA programs for teens in light of research that showed that problem-focused youth programming had only limited success. The "new" approach, "positive youth development," brought back some traditional YWCA girls work themes. Though the terms used to describe the program were of the 1990s, its aims hearkened back to the concept of the Girl Reserve as "a girl who is constantly storing up, putting in reserve, more of those qualities which will help her to take her place as a Christian citizen in her home, her school, her church, and her community."
The outcome of the study was the Youth Development Program, introduced in 1994. It sought to replace quick fixes for young people in crisis with long-term programming aimed at helping ten- to eighteen-year-olds develop to their full potential. While Community Associations continued their prevention and remediation programs for youth in high risk environments, the new approach emphasized "positive youth development" with core program themes of Empowerment, Health Promotion and Sports, Community and Leadership, and Family Life. National initiatives under this program included TechGYRLS, NetPrepGYRLS, the Mott Pregnancy Prevention Evaluation, YWCA/PepsiCo Girls Leadership Program, and a variety of sports and fitness programs for girls.
Administrative History
[1910] Secretaries for high schools, and private and preparatory schools under Student Committee in the Method Department
1911 Special Worker, Junior Work, under City Committee and Secretaries for high schools, and private and preparatory schools under Student Committee in the Method Department
1913 Secretary for Girls' Work under Method Department and Secretary for secondary schools in Student Committee
1919 Department name changed to Research and Method
1920 Secretaries for Girls' work; Girls' work, Colored; and secondary schools in Research and Method
1920 Feb Girls' Work Bureau
1923 Girl Reserve Department of Field Division
1932 Girl Reserve staff in Laboratory Division and National Services Division
1933 Special Worker in Laboratory Division (study on work with younger girls); and Girl Reserve Program in Leadership Division
1934-39 Girl Reserve Program in Leadership Division
1940-42 Group Interests in Community Division
1943-44 Program Staff ("Girl Reserve") in Community Division
1945 Constituency ("Younger Girls") in Community Division
1946 Constituency ("Teen-Age Program") in Community Division
1947 Community Division-headquarters based and regionally based
1950 Community Division, just headquarters based
1952 Leadership Services?
1959 Consultant, Teenage Program in Leadership Services
1960-70 Consultant, Teenage Program in Community Division
1971- Teen in Youth Constituencies (headquarters and region)
1977-83 Teen Program Consultant in Program Unit
1984-92? Teen Program Consultant and Teen Sexuality Education Program in Program Services Division
1994- Youth Development Program
Scope and Content
Records in this Subseries include general and historical files; department and committee records; conference records; program and project files; publications; reference materials; reports, studies, and a few scrapbooks and records from Community Association camps and clubs.
Because work with teenagers was seen as the future of the organization, all of the standard YWCA topics appear in the teen materials. Records related to "Girls Work" appear to have been gathered together and maintained as a category beginning with the staff reorganization after World War I. These records contain isolated earlier items, but researchers should also consult minutes of the Student Department (in RECORD GROUP 7), the Research and Method Department (in SERIES I of this Record Group), and reports by Junior Work and Girls' Work Field Secretaries in the City, Town, and Rural Communities Departments (in RECORD GROUP 8.)
The extensive Conference materials (primarily on the microfilm) can include: planning materials such as, local arrangements, mailings, study materials; items for use during the conference such as programs, schedules, handouts, training materials, daily meditations, skit scripts, song sheets, and bulletins with drawings and other art work, poetry and fiction by conference participants; summary materials such as reports, participants lists, financial, training materials, and evaluations. The records contain files on separate segregated conferences in the Southern Region up to 1946.
Programs and Projects files are mainly from the 1970s-90s and include projects related to employment, pregnancy prevention and sexuality education, empowerment and "development."
The extensive teen publications include handbooks and yearbooks for Girl Reserves and Y-Teens; program materials; educational materials on "citizenship," health, sex education, interpersonal relations, interracial relations, leadership, and World Fellowship; and manuals and training materials for staff and volunteers working with teens. The main teenage serial, The Bookshelf, is especially comprehensive, with articles written by a wide variety of National staff members. Subjects covered include nature study, interracial relations, child labor, employment/industrial issues, games, arts and crafts, sex education, health, nutrition, recreation, citizenship, psychology, vocations, and environmental conservation.
Secretaries' reports provide wonderful documentation of the expansion of the teen work in the 1920s and early 1930s. Studies include the main 1920s-40s YWCA studies of the teen field and an extensive 1998-99 survey of adolescent programs offered by Community YWCAs.
Microfilmed Records, 1906-70 only
[see Microfilmed Records Reel list]
For the years covered by the microfilm, the teen materials are much more extensive on microfilm than what has survived in original format, the major exception being publications. The Conference files are especially rich, and there are good materials about teen projects during World War II. Teen records can be found on the microfilm under:
Minutes and Reports
Girl Reserve Staff and Committee
Teenage Program Committee
Subject Files
Economics, [National YWCA] Consultation [on work with economically deprived adolescent girls], 1965-67
Fields and Field Work, Policy, Younger Girls
Girl Reserve
Industrial, Young Girls
Labor, Youth
Leadership, N.A.P.W., Girl Reserve [Section]
O.O. [Outside Organizations]--Religious, YMCA, Hi-Y
O.O. [Outside Organizations]--Youth
Social Work
Teen Age
Y-Teen
Original Format Records, 1907-2001, 15 linear feet
[see Original Format Records Folder List]
The Minutes and Reports were not discarded after filming and constitute the main overlap with the microfilmed materials. The original format materials contain a larger selection of publications, including the wonderful teen serial, The Bookshelf. Programs and Projects from the late 1960s into the 1990s are fairly well documented.
The Original Format Records are arranged as follows:
General and History
Department and Committees
Conferences, Consultations, and Workshops
Programs and Projects
Publications
Reference Materials
Reports
Studies
Miscellaneous
Related Materials
In other Subseries in this Series:
Additional materials about the Younger Girls in Business and Industry Clubs can be found in Subseries A. Employed Women.
One of the Studies in Subseries B. Immigration and Foreign Communities is on the American-born daughters of immigrants.
In other series in this Record Group:
Some of the earliest discussions of the teen work are in the Minutes of the Department of Research and Method in SERIES I. DEPARTMENT, STAFF, AND COMMITTEES. The reports include early reports of junior and girls work secretaries.
SERIES V. PROGRAM SUBJECTS has records related to teen work in Subseries A. Camping and Outdoor Recreation, Subseries C. Music (including Girl Reserve songs and songbooks and the 1965 Y-Teen Folksong Project), and Subseries B. Health (Sports and Fitness Programs for girls, 1990s).
The YWCA's main serial, the Association Monthly/Womans Press/YWCA Magazine in SERIES VI. PUBLICATIONS contains many articles related to teen-agers in the YWCA.
In other Record Groups:
Because it was the "representative and executive" committee of the National Association, the National Board's minutes in RECORD GROUP 2. PREDECESSOR ORGANIZATIONS AND NATIONAL BOARD contain many discussions of girls and teen work.
RECORD GROUP 4. CONVENTIONS AND CONFERENCES has information about National Teen Assembly and teen participation in Convention.
Work with high school students was initially the province of the Student Department in RECORD GROUP 7. STUDENT WORK. There are also records about Eight Week Clubs.
Visitation reports of secretaries are in SERIES I. SERVICES TO COMMUNITY ASSOCIATIONS of RECORD GROUP 8. COMMUNITY ASSOCIATIONS. The microfilmed records in SERIES IV. COMMUNITY ASSOCIATIONS FILES contain local studies of Teen Programs and needs.
RECORD GROUP 9. PHOTOGRAPHS contains many photographs of teen age program.
RECORD GROUP 10. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS includes the Youth Development Program videos "It's Okay to Say No Way!," "Lovesick," and "Crush." There are also audio and videotapes of some Teen Assemblies and Conferences from the late 1970s to the 1990s.
In personal papers:
The Elizabeth Steel Genne Papers contain additional information about the Teen Sexuality Education Project
SUBSERIES E. YOUNG ADULTS Historical Note
The Young Adult constituency was a product of the post World War II era. It encompassed all members between the ages of 18 and 35, whether or not they were in school or college, or employed outside of the home. The National Association had found that membership in its remaining constituent groups (the Councils for employed women, college students, and teenagers) had declined while the number of new "YW-Wives" groups for young homemakers was growing. Unable financially to support specialized staff for all of these groups, the National Association combined them. Young Adult staff were in Leadership Services, Membership Services, and the Community Division. They were given responsibility to facilitate the activities of the Councils, Assemblies, and YW-wives groups; to act as a resource; and to produce training and written materials.
The largest groups within the new Young Adult constituency were the College Students and Teenagers. These two groups each had unique needs: while most constituent groups within the YWCA were members of Community Associations, the College Students were responsible for administering their own Associations, and effective work with teenagers required specific training. The National Association maintained staff dedicated to these two groups, and their official association with the Young Adult constituency was relatively short-lived.